上一章我们看到了数论在密钥交换中是有用的
In the last module we saw that number
theory can be useful for key exchange.
本章我们将回顾一些数论的基本事实
In this modlule we will review some basic facts
of number theory that will help us build
下周它们会帮助我们构建很多公钥系统。
我们讲本章的内容时
many public key systems next week. As we
go through the material in this module it
时不时地暂停视频可以帮助大家确保理解所有例子
might help to pause the video from time to
time to make sure all the examples are clear
如我所说，我们要用数论来构建密钥交换协议
So as I said we're gonna use number
theory to build key exchange protocols.
我们将使用数论来构建数字签名，公钥加密
和许多其他东西
We're gonna use number theory to build
digital signatures, public encryption and many, many other things.
但在我们能做这些之前，我们必须回顾
But before we can do all that, we have to review some basic
数论里的一些基本事实，事实上在本章
我们将快速过一遍相关概念
facts from number theory and in fact in
this module we're gonna do a quick course
如果大家想在线下回顾这里讨论的内容
on the relevant concept. If you'd like to
review some of the material discussed in
我在本章最后引用了一本免费的Victor Shoup的教材
this module offline, I referenced at the
end of the module a free textbook by
我指出他书中的那么几章
Victor Shoup and I pointed to some
specific chapters in his book that will
可以解释我们这里讲的内容。那么从现在开始
explain the materials that we will cover
here. So from here on I'm going to use the
我将使用如下记法。我将总使用N来表示
following notation. I'm going to use
capital N to always denote a positive
正整数，我将总使用p来表示正质数
integer, and I'm going to use lower case p
to always denote a positive prime number.
现在我想引入如下记法，这个Z写得很有趣
Now I'd like to introduce the following
notation, there's this funny Z that's
有双对角线，还有一个下标N
written like two diagonal lines here with
a subscript N I'm gonna use that to denote
我用它来表示集合｛0,1,2,..,N-1｝
the sets as zero, one, two, up to N minus
one. This is actually a very common
这是密码学里非常通用的记号，我这里坚持使用它
notation that's used in Crypto, and so
I'll stick to that here. So again, Z sub N
Z_N表示从0到N-1的整数集合。事实上
denotes the set of integers 0,1 up to N-1. And in fact, this is not just a
这不仅仅是一个整数集合。我们可以在上面做加法和乘法
set of integers. We can do addition and
multiplication in this set as long as we
只要我们始终取模N即可。对于了解代数的人来说
always multiply module of the number N.
For those of you who know a little bit of
我说Z_N表示了一个环，其加法和乘法
algebra, I'll just say that Z sub N
denotes a ring where addition and
都定义为模N的。这是密码学里的非常常用的记号
multiplication are done modulo N. This is
very common notation in crypto, although
尽管在现代数学里Z_N有时表示其他东西
in modern mathematics Z sub N sometimes
denotes something else. But as I said I'm
(这里说的可能是p进整数环Z_p)
但如我所说，我将继续使用Z_N表示
整数集合｛0,1,..,N-1｝
gonna keep on using Z sub N to denote the
set of integers 0 to N-1 with
以及模N的加法和乘法。那么我想确保大家
addition and multiplication modulo N. So
I want to make sure everybody's
都能适应模算术。那么我们来看个数，比如说N=12
comfortable with modular arithmetic. And
so let's just look at the number, say, N=12
我们来看模算术的一些基本事实
And let's just see some basic facts about modular arithmetic. So
我说，9+8=17；17=5 mod 12
I'm gonna say that nine plus eight is
seventeen; seventeen is five modulo
所以我写9+8=5在Z_12中
twelve, so I'm gonna write that nine plus
eight is equal to five in Z 12. Now
现在有没有人能告诉我们5乘7在Z_12里是多少？
换句话说，5乘7模12是多少？
can someone tell me how much is five times
seven in Z12? In other words, how much is modular 12?
5乘7是35。大家知道36被12整除
Well, five times seven is 35. And if you recall, 36 is divisible by 12
所以5乘7是-1模12。35 = -1 mod 12
So five times seven is really -1 module of 12. 35 is minus
但-1 mod 12与11是一样的
one module of twelve. But minus one module
of 12 is basically the same as 11,
因为我加12到-1上，就得到11。下一个问题是
cuz I just add 12  to -1 and I
get 11. And the next question is, how
5-7在Z_12中是多少？5-7=-2
much is 5 - 7 in the Z12?
Well, 5-7 is -2.
-2 mod 12。我把12加到-2上，得到10。因此
-2 modulo 12, well, I just add 12
to -2 and I get 10. As a result,
我们说，5-7=10 mod 12。这只是确保
we say that 5 - 7 is equal to
10. So again, this is just to make sure
大家对这种Z_12的记法都能适应。换句话说，工作在模12下
everybody is comfortable with this notation of working
in Z12. In other words, working in modulo 12.
我只想进行一个推广，事实上
Now, I'd just like to make a
general statement that, in fact,
Z_N上的算术，换句话说，模N的算术
arithmetic in ZN, in other words,
arithmetic modulo N works just as you
正如大家所期待的那样工作。例如，所有的
你知道的关于加法和乘法的运算法则
would expect. So, for example, all the
laws that you know about addition and
在Z_N中也同样适用。例如，分配律
multiplication work equally well in ZN.
For example, the distributive law, X times
X*(Y+Z)=X*Y+X*Z
Y plus Z, is still gonna be equal to X
times Y plus X times Z. So many of the
工作在整数或者实数上的时候，
很多大家知道的关于算术的事实
things that you know about arithmetic when
working over the integers or in the reals,
在Z_N中也成立，即工作在模N上
will translate to working in, ZN, namely
working modulo N.
我们需要的下一个概念叫做最大公约数，或gcd
So the next concept we need is what's called a greatest common
divisor, or a GCD. And so suppose they
假设给你两个整数X和Y。我们说X和Y的gcd是
give you two integers X and Y. We say that
the GCD of X and Y is basically the
它们的最大共有因数，最大的可以同时整除
greatest common divisor it's the largest
number, the largest integer that divides
X和Y的整数。例如，gcd(12,18)是什么？
both X and Y. So for example, what is the
GCD of 12 and 18?
gcd是6，因为6同时整除12和18
Well the GCD is 6, because 6 divides both 12
and 18,
而且6是最大的能同时整除12和18的整数
and it's the largest number that divides both 12 and 18.
gcd的一个重要事实是，如果我给你两个数X,Y
Now there is an important fact about GCD's in particular, if I give you two numbers, two integers X and Y, there will always exist
总是存在另外两个整数，我记为A和B，使得A*X+B*Y
two other integers, I will call them A and
B, such that if I look at A times X + B
是X和Y的gcd。换句话说，gcd(X,Y)
times Y what I get is the GCD of X and Y.
In other words the GCD of X and Y is a
是X和Y的一个线性组合，使用整数A和B
linear combination of X and Y using the
integers A and B. So far let us look at a
到这里我们看一个简单的例子，我们看之前12和18的gcd
simple example, here, let's look at the
GCD from before, so the integers for the
这两整数的gcd是2*12-1*18，也就是24-18
GCD would be 2 times 12 Minus 1
times 18. That's 24 minus 18,
等于6=gcd(12,18)。所以A和B在这种情况下
分别为2和-1
which is equal to 6. So the integers A
and B in this case would be 2 and -1
但这仅仅是一个例子，事实上，整数A和B
But this is just an example, and in
fact, these integers, A and B will exist
对任意整数X和Y都存在。A和B不仅存在，事实上
for any integers, X and Y. Now not only do
A and B exist, in fact there's a very
(根据整数模N乘法群中逆元的存在性，可知A和B存在但不唯一)
有一个简单有效的算法，可以找到这些整数A和B
simple and efficient algorithm to find
these integers, to find A and B. The
这个算法被称为扩展的欧几里德算法
algorithm is what's called the extended
Euclidean algorithm. This is actually one
这是古希腊时代最优美的算法之一，当然由欧几里德提出
of the prettiest algorithms from ancient
Greek times, due to Euclid of course. I'm
我这里不给大家展示这个算法的工作过程
not gonna show you how this algorithm
works here, I. It's a fairly simple
这个算法很简单，告诉大家，事实上给定X和Y
algorithm. I'll just tell that in fact
given X and Y, this algorithm will find A
在X和Y的对数的平方的时间里找到A和B
and B in time roughly quadratic in the
logarithms of X and Y. We'll come back to
我们以后会回来讨论欧几里德算法的性能的
that and discuss the, the performance of
Euclid's algorithm I have a bit more
我待会会有更多细节。但现在我们只需知道
detail in just a minute. But, for now all
we need to know is that A and B can
A和B可以被有效地找到。现在，如果gcd(X,Y)=1
actually be found efficiently. Now, if the
GCD of X and Y happens to be 1. In other
换句话说，1是X和Y的最大公约数，那么我们说
words, 1 is the largest integer that
divides both X and Y, then we say that X
X和Y是互质的。例如，3和5的gcd
and Y are relatively prime. For example,
the GCD of three and five, it's not
不难看出正好是1，因为3和5都是质数
difficult to see that it hap, that happens
to be 1, Because both 3 and 5 are
我们需要讨论的下一话题是模逆
prime. The next topic we need to talk
about is modular inversion. So other
(数和它的逆的乘法结果等于单位元，即1)
不是我们已知的有理数的逆，换句话说
than rationals we know what the inverse of
a number is. In other words if I give you
如果给你一个数2，2的逆是1/2
the number 2 the inverse of 2 is
simply the fraction one half.
问题是当我们工作在模N上时，逆是什么
the question is what about inverses when we, we
work module N. Well, so the inverse of
那么Z_N中的一个元素X的逆，就是Z_N中的另一元素Y
an element X in Z N is simply another
element Y in Z N such that X times Y is
使得X乘以Y等于Z_N中的1.换句话说，X*Y=1 mod N
equal to 1 in Z N. In other words X
times Y is equal to 1 modulo N. And this
这个数Y记为X^-1。不难看出，如果Y存在
number Y is denoted by X inverse. And it's
not difficult to see that if, if Y exists,
那么事实上它是唯一的。如我所说，我们会使用X^-1
then in fact it's unique. And as I said,
we'll use X inverse to denote the inverse
来表示X的逆。那么我们来看一个简单例子。
假设N是某个奇数
of X. So let's look at a quick example.
Suppose N is some odd integer, and I ask
我问大家，在Z_N中2的逆是什么？不难看出
you what is the inverse of 2 in ZN?
So it's not too difficult to see that the
在Z_N中2的逆是(N+1)/2，大家可以看到
inverse of two in ZN in fact is N plus one
over 2 and you can see that this is an
这是一个整数，因为N是奇数，N+1就是偶数，所以
integer because N is odd, therefore, N+1 is even and, therefore, (N+1)/2
(N+1)/2事实上是一个整数，要求范围是从1到N
is in fact an integer and the
range 1..N as required. Now why is (N+1)/2
为什么(N+1)/2是2的逆呢？我们就把它乘以2
the inverse of two?
Well, let's just multiply the 2 so we do
2*(N+1)/2，得到什么？等于N+1
2 times (N+1) over 2 and what do
we get? Well, that's simply equal to N+1
在Z_N中，N+1等于1。由于它们的乘积等于1
and N+1 is simply equal to
1 in ZN. So since their product is equal
我们知道(N+1)/2是2在Z_N中的逆
to 1. We know that (N+1)/2
is the inverse of 2 in ZN.
现在我们理解了模逆是什么了，问题是
Now we understand what a modular inverse is, the
question is which elements actually have
Z_N中哪些元素有逆？有一个简单的引理是说
an inverse in ZN? And so there's a very
simple lemma that says that if for an
如果Z_N中的一个元素X有逆，当且仅当
element X in ZN, that element has
an inverse if and only if it is relatively
X与N互质。我再说一遍
prime to the modulus N, to the number N.
So I'll say that again. X in ZN is
X在Z_N中可逆，当且仅当X与N互质。我们快速证明之
invertible if and only if X is relatively
prime to N. And let's quickly prove that.
容易看成，假设gcd(X,N)=1
It's actually fairly simple to see. So
suppose a GCD of X and N happens to be
那么X与N互质，根据gcd的性质
equal to one. So X is relatively prime to
N. Well, by this property of GCD as we
我们知道存在整数A和B，满足AX+BN
know that there exists integers A and B.
Such that A times X plus B times N is
等于X和N的gcd，也就是1，所以AX+BN=1
equal to the GCD of X and N, which happens
to be one. So A times X plus B times N is
现在我们可以取这里的方程
equal to 1. Now we can actually take
this equation here and, and us it reduce
两边取模N，意思是在Z_N中，AX=1
it's modulo N. So what this means is that
A times X is equal to one in Z_N. Once we
只要我们对这个方程取模N，这一项会被消除
reduce this equation modulo N this term
simply falls off because B times N is
因为BN被N整除，因此是0模N。我们刚刚证明了
divisible by N and therefore is 0
modulo N. But what we just showed is that
事实上X在Z_N中的逆就是A。所以因为X与N互质
in fact X inverse is simply A in ZN. So
because X is relatively prime to N, we
我们可以证明X可逆，并且构造出了X^-1 mod N
were able to show that X is invertible by
actually building the inverse of X modulo N
那么引理的另一个方向呢？如果gcd大于1会怎样？
Now what about the other direction?
What happens if the GCD is greater than 1?
(不知不觉就用了逆否命题)
那么我们想证明没有逆。这也是容易看出的
Then we want to show that there is no
inverse. But that's actually very easy to
因为这里，如果你说A正好是X的模N逆
see because in this case, if you claim
that A happens to be the inverse of X
我们看AX，AX=1 mod N
modulo N, well, let's look at AX; AX we know should be equal to 1 modulo N
但是如果gcd(X,N)>1，那么gcd(AX,N)>1
But if the GCD(X,N) is bigger than 1, then the GCD(AX,N)
但是如果gcd(AX,N)>1
is bigger than one. But, if the GCD
of A times X and N is bigger than 1,
那么AX不可能等于1
then it's not possible that AX is
equal to 1. So AX must also be
所以AX必须也大于1，因此A不可能是X的模N逆
bigger than 1, and therefore, A cannot
be the inverse of X module N.
这就证明了事实上，当gcd大于1，X不可能有逆
So this proves that, in fact, in, when the GCD is
greater than 1, X cannot have an
因为没有A，使得AX=1 mod N
inverse, because there is no A, such that
A times X is equal to one modulo N
这可能有点令人费解，最好能有个例子
And this might be a bit confusing, so you
might be best just to, do an example. So
那么我们看，假设gcd(X,N)=2
let's look at, let's suppose that the GCD
of X and N happens to be equal to 2.
我声称因此X不是模N可逆的，为什么？
I claim that X is therefore, is not
invertible modular N. Well, why is that
对于所有的A，我们知道AX一定是偶数
true? Well, for all A, we know that A
times X is gonna be even, is even. And the
原因是，因为2整除X，2整除N
reason we know that is because, well, 2
divides X and 2 divides N. Well, since
因为2乘除X，2就整除AX，因此AX一定是偶数
two divide X, 2 is also gonna divide A
times X. And therefore, A times X must be
这意味着不可能有AX=1 mod N
even. But what that means is that there's
no way that A times X is equal to 1 modulo N
特别地，不可能有AX=BX+1
In particular, there's no way
that A times X is equal to B times N + 1
这不可能发生，这个等式不可能成立
This simply can't happen, this
equality must not hold. Because this side
因为我没说过这边是偶数，同样的道理，BN也是偶数
happens to be even, as we said. B times N
for exactly the same reason is also even:
N被2整除，因此BN也被2整除
N is divisible by two; therefore B times N
is also divisible by two. So therefore B
因此BN+1是奇数。因为偶数不可能等于奇数
times N+1 is odd. And since even
can't equal to odd, it's not possible that
所以对任意的整数B，AX=BN+1都不可能成立。特别地
A times X is equal to some multiple of N+1. And in particular this means
这意味着A不可能是X的逆，因为AX不可能是1 mod N
that A cannot be the inverse of X because
A times X cannot be 1 mod N so X is not
所以X不是模N逆的。现在我们有了对逆的完整理解
invertible modular N. So now we have a
complete understanding of what are the
我们知道一个元素是可逆的，当且仅当
invertible elements. Basically, we know
that an element is invertible if and only
它和N互质。我喜欢这个证明的地方在于
if it's relatively prime to N. And what I
like about this proof is I would say this
这是所谓的计算机科学的证明。不仅仅为大家证明了
is what's called a computer-science proof
In the sense that not only does it prove
而且还为大家展示了如何有效地计算这个逆
to you that the inverse exists; it also
shows you how to efficiently calculate the
我们计算逆的方法是
inverse. And the way we calculate the
inverse, is basically by using this
使用这个递减算法。定义数A和B
extending decreasing algorithm. Define the
numbers A and B. And once we found the
我们一旦找到数A和B，就结束了。因为A就是X的逆
numbers A and B, we done because A is the
inverse of X. And the numbers A and B can
数A和B可以被有效地找到，我已经为大家展示了
be found very efficiently. So along the
way I've also shown you an algorithm for
计算模N逆的算法
inverting elements, modulo N.
再忍一会，我们再引入一些记法。
我们记Z_N^*为Z_N中所有可逆元素
Okay. So bear with me, and let's introduce this little more notation. So we're gonna denote by ZN star as the set of invertible elements in
换句话说，Z_N^*是Z_N中所有
满足gcd(X,N)=1的元素组成的集合
Z N. In other words, ZN* is the set
of all elements in ZN such that GCD(X,N)=1
但我希望大家把Z_N^*当作
Okay. But I want you, again, to think of ZN* as
Z_N中所有可逆的元素。那么我们看几个例子
basically those elements in ZN that have
an inverse. So let's look at a few
我们从一个质数p开始。我们知道，
从0到p-1的所有整数
examples. So let's start with a prime p.
We know that of the integers from zero to
都与p互质
p-1, all of them are gonna be
relatively primed to p except one
除了一个整数0，0与p不互质
integer--namely, the integer 0. Zero is
not relatively primed to P, because the
因为gcd(p,0)=0不是1，所以如果p是质数
GCD(p,0)=0, not 1. So therefore, if p is a prime, the set ZP*
Z_p^*就是Z_P除去0，意味着Z_p中的所有元素都是可逆的
is simply ZP minus 0, which means
that everything in Z_P is invertible
0除外。所以如果想计算Z_p^*的大小，答案就是p-1
except for 0. So if you like the size
of ZP*, it's simply P-1. Now
我们再看我们最喜欢的整数。
为什么不告诉我Z_12^*是什么呢？
let's look at our favorite integer again.
So why don't you tell me what is Z12*?
模12可逆的所有元素组成的集合是什么？
What is the set of invertible elements modulo 12?
答案当然是，所有与12互质的数
And the answer, of course, is all the numbers
that are relatively primed to 12--namely,
也就是1,5,7和11。那么，比如3,4,6不是可逆的
1, 5, 7, and 11. So, for example, 3, 4, 6--all of those are
因为它们与12的gcd不是1
not invertible because they all have a, a
non-trivial GCD with twelve, And as we
我们说过，如果我给你一个Z_N^*里的元素X
said before, if I give you an element X
in ZN*, you can find its inverse
你可以使用扩展的欧几里德算法找出它的逆。
事实上你可以很有效地找出它的逆
using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
You can find its inverse very efficiently,
使用这个算法。我们刚才学了如何去解
in fact, using this algorithm. So what we
just learned is basically how to solve
线性同余方程。换句话说，如果我给你一个线性方程
modular linear equations. In other words,
if I give you a linear equation and I ask
我让你在模N下解出来，这是非常容易的
you to solve it mod N, it's actually very
easy to do. All you do is you move B to
你只需把B移到另一边，那么你就有了一个-B，
然后再乘以A的逆
the other side so you have a minus B, and
then you multiply by A inverse. So the
那么答案是B*A^-1。大家可以使用欧几里德算法找到A^-1
answer is minus B times A inverse. And you
can find A inverse using the Euclidean
一旦你有了一个逆，用-B乘以它
algorithm. And once you have a inverse,
you'd simply multiply it by minus B,
取模N，得到这个线性方程的解
modulo N, and that gives you the solution
to this linear equation. Now the
现在欧几里德算法实际上花掉log N的平方的时间
Euclidian algorithm actually takes time
that's quadratic in logarithm of N. So it
所以它花的时间与(log N)^2成正比。因此我们说
takes time proportional to log squared N.
And as a result we say that this is a
这是一个平方算法，对于解模N的线性方程而言
quadratic algorithm for solving linear
equations, modulo N, and in fact this is
事实上这是已知的最好的算法。如果你回想一下
高中时期的代数内容
the best know algorithm. And so if you
think back to your high-school algebra
当你学了如何解线性方程后，下一个问题是
days, after you learned how to solve
linear equations, the next question was,
怎么解二次方程。这个问题很有趣
well, what about quadratic equations. And
that problem is actually quite
我们下面几节看
interesting, and we're gonna see that in
the next few segments.